Guide to the Yale Collection of American Literature Letter Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- "P"
  - PENNELL, JOSEPH, 1857-1926, 2 (Box 23, Folder 849-850)
    - Original design, with ms notes and directions, for the title-page of Edgar Saltus's The Gardens of Aphrodite, the first book issued by the Pennell club
      [Removed from: Za copy of the book]
      Gift of Louis M. Rabinowitz, February 1943
    - Sizer, Theodore, 1880-. Pennell in a true light, [New Haven, 1930]
      Caption title
      Typescript of a review of The life and letters of Joseph Pennell by E. R. Pennell, Boston, 1929, for The Yale review, v. XX, no. 2, December. 1930, p. 425-427
  - PENNSYLVANIA HALL ASSOCIATION, PHILA. COMMITTEE (Box 23, Folder 851)
    - 2 ALS to Theodore D(wight) Weld, Philadelphia, 1837, 1838
  - PENNYPACKER, ISAAC RUSLING, 1852-1935 (Box 23, Folder 852)
    - 2 ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Mount Holly, N. J., 1889, 1890
      Removed from: his Gettysburg and other poems...Philadelphia, 1890
      Za.P385.890g.copy 1, 2
  - PERKINS, FRANCES, 1880-1965 (Box 23, Folder 853)
    - TLS to James T(inkham) Babb, Washington, D. C., 1951 February 28
      With a copy of Mr. Babb's reply
  - PERRY, BLISS, 1860-1954 (Box 23, Folder 854)
    - ALS to the Youth's Companion, Princeton, N. J., 1898 March 7
      Concerning changes in "my Memorial Day story"
      Purchased from Charles Hamilton, April 15, 1958 with 4 others from Alvord fund
  - PERRY, NORA, 1831-1896 (Box 23, Folder 855)
    - Cressid [poem], autograph ms
      20 lines, Signed
    - 2 ALS to Charlotte (Hastings) Whipple, Providence, 1879
    - 2 ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Melrose Highlands, Mass., 1885 January 3, 27
      1 page, 1 leaf; 1 leaf
      [Removed from: her New songs and ballads, Boston, 1887
      Za.P427.887n]
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Boston, 1890 October 28
      [Removed from: Za copy of her Another Flock of Girls, Boston, 1890]
      Alvord fund, January 1943
  - PERSHING, JOHN J. (JOHN JOSEPH), 1860-1948 (Box 23, Folder 856)
    - TLS to Colonel George Harvey, Washington, D. C., 1920 March 9
      Gift of Elizabeth Anderson, November 1951
  - PETERSON, ARTHUR, 1851-1932 (Box 23, Folder 857)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Philadelphia, 1900 October 7
      1 page with addressed envelope
      Removed from: his Collected poems... Phila., 1900
  - PETERSON, HENRY, 1818-1891 (Box 23, Folder 858)
    - 2 ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Philadelphia, 1888 February 13, 15
      Removed from: Arthur Peterson's Songs of New-Sweden...Phila., 1887 and His Caesar...Phila., 1879
  - PFEIFFER, EMIL CHARLES (Box 23, Folder 859)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Cambridge, Mass., [1889] July 22
  - PHELPS, CHARLES HENRY (Box 23, Folder 860)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, San Francisco, 1880 May 24
      Removed from: his Californian verses...San Francisco, 1882
      Za.P5118.882v
  - PHILLIPS, WENDELL, 1811-1884, 2 (Box 23, Folder 861-862)
    - ALS to "Dear Sir," [n. p.], undated
      Removed from Abraham Lincoln by Nicolay and Hay
    - Card of admission, signed, [n. p.], January 7
    - ALS to Miss Thayer, Boston, Mass., [1882] December 2
  - PIATT, JOHN JAMES, 1835-1917 (Box 23, Folder 863)
    - Charity at Home. AMS of poem, dated, 1897 April 22
      Removed from: His...Little new- world idyls...1893
    - Farther. AMS of sonnet, dated, 1897 April 22
      Removed from: His Idyls and lyrics...1881
    - The Ghost's Entry. AMS of poem, dated, 1897 April 22
      Removed from: His The nests at Washington...1864
    - To the Statue on the Capitol at Washington, Looking Eastward at Dawn. AMS of 3 stanzas
      Removed from: His Landmarks. The lost farm...1877
    - 2 ALS to Thomas Hutchinson, Dublin, 1893, 1897
      1 leaf; 4 pages (1 leaf)
      Removed from: His A return to paradise...1891 and His The ghost's entry...1895
      With: At Morning. AMS of poem, dated June 21, 1893, and addressed to Thomas Hutchinson. On stationery of the Consulate of the United States at Dublin
      Removed from: His The ghost's entry...1895
    - 2 ALS to Editor of the Overland Monthly, Cleves, Ohio, 1871 May, September
      1 leaf; 1 leaf
      Removed from: His Landmarks...1872 and His Poems of house and home...1879
    - ALS to Mr. Townsend, Cincinnati, 1869 December 19
      Removed from: His Poems in the sunshine and firelight...1866 Gift of Owen F. Aldis, 1911
  - PIATT, SARAH M. B. (SARAH MORGAN BRYAN), 1836-1919 (Box 23, Folder 864)
    - ALS to [William?] Young, North Bend, Ohio, [c1890?]
    - Beatrice Cenci (in a City Shop-Window), Autograph ms poem (incomplete?), signed: S. M. B. Piatt, Clevis, Hamilton Co., Ohio, undated
    - One from the Dead, AMS of poem
    - My Artist, to A. V. P. - Nat. 1864, Autograph ms of poem
    - The Witch in the Glass. AMS of poem, dated, 1897 April 22
  - PICKETT, LA SALLE CORBELL, 1848-1931 (Box 23, Folder 865)
    - ALS to "My dear friend," Washington, D. C., 1893 September 30
  - PIERPONT, JOHN, 1785-1866, 2 (Box 23, Folder 866-867)
    - ANS to Miss Catharine Putnam, [Boston], 1843 December 24
      Plain funds, May 1943
    - ALS to William B. Fowle, Boston, 1847 December 24
      Concerns his American first class book
      Removed from: Emily Taylor's Lays for the Sabbath...1846
    - Ms document, entirely in his hand, with his signature. Litchfield, 1834 May 17
      Together with a small photograph, taken shortly before his death
      Gift of Miss Lucy M. Pierpont, May 1939
    - Bibliography of works published 1812-1850. Autograph ms in Pierpont's hand, with envelope addressed to Rev. Charles Brooks
      8 numbered leaves
      Removed from: His Airs of Palestine, Baltimore, 1816
    - Ruins at Paestum. Ms
      Written in double columns
      With fragment of an ALS from the author to an unidentified correspondent containing what is presumably a reference to this manuscript
  - PIKE, ALBERT, 1809-1891, 4 (Box 24, Folder 868-871)
    - ALS to George W(alker) Crawford, Little Rock, Ark., 1850 January 16
      2 pages with address leaf
      Concerning the pay of William Totten
      Purchased on Beinecke Western Americana funds, June 1980
    - ALS to Benjamin W. Austin, Washington, D. C., 1887 March 6
      Purchased from Emily Driscoll, November 29, 1956, McClintock fund
    - ALS to George W. Light, Van Buren, Ark. Territory, 1833 May 25
      1 leaf with address on reverse
      Typed transcript, 1 leaf
      Removed from: His Prose sketches and poems...Boston, 1834 Gift of Owen F. Aldis, 1911
    - Typewritten copy of an ALS to George W. Light, Van Buren, 1833 May 26
      Gift of J. Hugo Tatsch, May 10, 1933
    - ALS to Darwin C. Pavey, Washington, 1887 July 12
      Removed from: His Morals and dogma... 1871
    - ALS to General Marcus J. Wright, [Washington], 1883 October 10
      Removed from: His Morals and dogma...1871
    - ALS and 1 stanza of poetry, signed, Little Rock, Ark., 1846 June 5
      Addressed to Rev. Wm. B. Sprague, Albany, New York
      Removed from: His Hymn to the gods... [? 1872]
    - APCS to Geo. Alfred Townsend, Washington, 1873 September 21
      Mounted in folder with ALS from Theo(dore) H. Emmons to Bro. Day, Boston, September 29, 1894. 1 leaf, concerning the poem "Every Year" by Albert Pike
    - ALS to Edmund C. Stedman, Washington, 1888 January 24
      Mounted in folder with portrait and clippings
    - Song. AMS of 5 stanzas, dated, 1865
      Mounted in folder with ALS to E. C. Stedman, January. 24, 1888
  - PINCKNEY, JOSEPHINE, 1895-1957 (Box 24, Folder 872)
    - 6 ALS, 4 APCS and 17 TLS to Prentiss Taylor, Charleston, S. C. and New York, [1933]-1947
      With 6 original envelopes
  - PITCHER, JAMES, 1845- (Box 24, Folder 873)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Hartwick Seminary, 1896 November 30
  - PLATT, CHARLES D. (CHARLES DAVID), 1856-1923 (Box 24, Folder 874)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Wallingford, Conn., 1907 August 10
  - POLLOCK, CHANNING, 1880-1946 (Box 24, Folder 875)
    - The Enemy
      Typescript (carbon) of prompt script: [4], 7, [4], 40 [i.e. 42], [4], 41 [i.e. 42], [3], 39, [3], 28 numbered leaves
      With 7 leaves of revisions inserted
      With ms corrections and revisions by the author. Signed. Anonymous gift, 1960
  - POND, FREDERICK EUGENE, 1856-1925 (Box 24, Folder 876)
    - 2 ALS to William McK. Heath, Westfield, Wis. and New York, 1878, 1882
      Plain funds, 1942
  - POOLE, ERNEST, 1880-1950 (Box 24, Folder 877)
    - TLS to Mr. Robert Bridges, New York, 1918 June 6
      With reply
  - PORTER, CHARLOTTE (Box 24, Folder 878)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Cambridge, 1907 December 5
      1 leaf with addressed envelope
  - PORTER, HORACE (Box 24, Folder 879)
    - ALS to E. C. Stedman, [New York], 1866 May 15
      Gen. Porter, West Point, 1860
  - PORTER, KATHERINE ANNE, 1890-1980 (Box 24, Folder 880)
    - TPCS to Louis Martz, Washington, D. C., 1962 January 25
  - PORTER, NATHANIEL, 1727-1775, undated (Box 24, Folder 881)
    Empty Folder
    Item now catalouged under YCAL MSS MISC Group 545 F-1.
  - POTTER, JEFFERY WATSON (Box 24, Folder 882)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, New York, 1902 May 9
  - POTTLE, EMERY BEMSLEY, 1875- (Box 24, Folder 883)
    - 1 ALS and 1 AL to "Mary," Lago di Como, Italy, and n. p., [1911 September 10]
      Signed: "Bambino"
    - In a Garden [poem], typescript (original)
      Signed
    - Mystery [poem], manuscript, Signed ("Bambino")
    - The House of the Heart [poem], typescript (original)
    - Morning by the Sea [poem], typescript (carbon)
    - Her Memory [poem], typescript (original)
      6 lines
    - The Grey Shore Calls [poem] typescript (original)
    - Hush [poem], typescript (original)
      Signed ("Bambino Angelico")
    - Her Coming [poem], typescript (original)
      With ms corrections by the author
      Signed (initials)
  - POTTS, CHARLES E. (Box 24, Folder 884)
    - ALS to E. C. Steadman [sic], Troy, 1891 December 25
  - POWERS, HORATIO NELSON, 1826-1890 (Box 24, Folder 885)
    - 3 ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Piermont, and Bridgeport, Conn., 1880-1887
      1 addressed "My dear friend"
  - PRENTICE, GEORGE D. (GEORGE DENISON), 1802-1870 (Box 24, Folder 886)
    - Signature on card, undated
  - PRESCOTT, MARY NEWMARCH, 1849-1888 (Box 24, Folder 887)
    - The Farmer's Lesson: Ms copy of poem, five stanzas, in her hand and signed
  - PRESCOTT, WILLIAM HICKLING, 1796-1859, 2 (Box 24, Folder 888-889)
    - 3 ALS to Edwin P. Whipple, Beacon St. [Boston], [and] Nahant, undated, [1847]
      2 pages, 1 page with address,
    - ALS to [James] Brown, Bedford, Vt., 1841 May 26
      Removed from: His History of the reign of Ferdinand and Isabella, Boston, 1838
    - ALS to Epes Sargent Dixwell, [n. p.], 1842 May 16
      Agreeing to attend an exhibition
      Removed from: v. 1 of his Conquest of Mexico
      Gift of Brewer (Owen library)
    - ALS to Peter S. DuPonceau, Boston, 1844 February 10
      Removed from: His History of the Conquest of Mexico, Phila., 1861
    - ALS to G. P. Putnam, Beacon Street [Boston], Monday eve, undated
    - ALS. Beacon St. [Boston], [1854] January 11
      Removed from: His History of the reign of Philip II, Boston, 1856
    - ALS to "My dear Sir," Boston, Mass., 1848 August 5
      Presenting his son
  - PRESTON, H. W. (HARRIET WATERS), 1836-1911 (Box 24, Folder 890)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, enclosing specimen translation: London, 1888
  - PRESTON, MARGARET JUNKIN, 1820-1897 (Box 24, Folder 891)
    - TLS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Lexington, Va., 1887 October 21
  - PROCTOR, EDNA DEAN, 1829-1923 (Box 24, Folder 892)
    - 5 ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Framingham, Mass., [and] Peoria, Ill., 1889-1899
      5 leaves with 3 envelopes
    - ALS to "My dear Friend," Brooklyn, 1859 May 17
    - [Heroes], autograph ms
      Lines 29-32 of the poem, signed and dated 1890
      (of 40 lines)
      Poem printed in her Poems (1890) p. 212
      Gift of Kenneth Cameron, 1957
  - PROUDFIT, DAVID LAW, 1842-1897 (Box 24, Folder 893)
    - 3 ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, New York, 1878, 1888
  - PRYOR, ROGER A. (ROGER ATKINSON), 1828-1919 (?) (Box 24, Folder 894)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, New York, 1889 September 16
      Removed from: Za copy of Virginius Dabney's Gold that did not glitter... Phila., 1889
  - PUTNAM, JAMES O. (JAMES OSBORNE), 1818-1903 (Box 24, Folder 895)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Buffalo, 1880 April 2
      [Removed from: William Bull Wright's
      The brook and other poems. New York, 1873.
      Za.W9373.873p]
  - PUTNAM, SAMUEL P. (SAMUEL PORTER), 1838-1896 (Box 24, Folder 896)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, New York, 1886 February 11
      Removed from: his Adami and Heva... New York, [1886?]
  - PYWON, ISIDOR (Box 24, Folder 897)
    - ANS to Mary Colum, New York, 1934 May 16
      [Removed from: his Croucher by the fires, New York (c1933)]
- "Q"
  - QUINCY, JOSIAH PHILLIPS, 1829-1910 (Box 24, Folder 898)
    - ANS. Boston, 1860 September 20
      [Removed from: Charicles... Boston, 1856. Za.Q4.856c]
- "R"
  - RABB, KATE MILNER, 1866-1937 (Box 24, Folder 899)
    - ALS to Merle (De Vore) Johnson, Indianapolis, Ind., 1908 June 12
  - RAINES, LESTER (Box 24, Folder 900)
    - AN signed with initials, to Carl Van Vechten, n. p., 1935 August 12
      [Removed from: his More New Mexico Writers, Las Vegas, 1935, Is50.r934r v. 2]
      Gift of Carl Van Vechten, 1941
  - RAND, KENNETH, b. 1891 (Box 24, Folder 901)
    - ALS to Professor Edward Bliss Reed, St. Augustine, Fla., [1915] March 31
  - RANDALL, JAMES RYDER, 1839-1908 (Box 24, Folder 902)
    - ANS to Henry F. Lamb, Augusta, Ga., 1891 February 2
      Removed from: his Maryland, my Maryland. Baltimore, Md., (c1908)
      Za.R157.908m
  - RANDOLPH, ARTHUR DAVIES FITZ (Box 24, Folder 903)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, New York, 1900 March 16
  - RANDOLPH, L. V. F. (LEWIS VAN SYCKEL FITZ), 1838-1921 (Box 24, Folder 904)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, New York, 1900 November 24
      [Removed from: his Survivals... New York, 1900. Za.R1588.900s]
  - RANSOM, JOHN CROWE, 1888-1974 (Box 24, Folder 905)
    - Lyrics Important, Sometimes Rude. Typescript review of Song and Idea by Richard Eberhart
      With author's corrections
  - RAYMOND, GEORGE LANSING, 1839-1929 (Box 24, Folder 906)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Princeton, N. J., 1893 March 11
      [Removed from: his Poetry as a representative art...New York, 1886. Za.R215.886p]
  - RAYNOLDS, ROBERT (Box 24, Folder 907)
    - ANS to Professor William Lyon Phelps, Newtown, Conn., 1941 October 19
      [Removed from: a copy of his Boadicea,, 1941-call no. Iy.R219.941b]
      Gift of Professor Phelps, December 1941
  - READ, THOMAS BUCHANAN, 1822-1872 (Box 24, Folder 908)
    - The Red, White and Blue. Autograph ms of a song in 4 stanzas, Rome, 1861 June 28
      1 leaf, 3 numbered leaves
      With clipping
      Removed from: his Poetical works...1866, v. 3
    - ALS to Messrs. Williams and Everett, Brooklyn, 1859 January 20
      2 leaves [3 pages]
      Removed from: [Townsend, Henry Clay] A memoir of Thomas Buchanan Read...1889
    - ALS to Mr. Putnam, Cincinnati, 1852 April 20
      Removed from: His Poems...1852
    - ALS to James T. Fields, Cincinnati, 1862 November 27
      Removed from: His Wagoner of the Alleghanies, Phila., 1863 Gift of Owen F. Aldis, 1911
    - ALS to James T. Fields, Philadelphia, 1853 June 10
      Removed from: his Poems...1853
    - ALS to -- Brainard, Philadelphia, 1848 March 22
      [Removed from: Za copy of his Poems, Boston, 1847]
    - ALS to Rev. Wm. R. Alger, Boston, 1860 May 20
      Removed from: his Poems...1860, v. 1
  - REESE, LIZETTE WOODWORTH, 1856-1935 (Box 24, Folder 909)
    - Books. Ms six-line poem in her own hand. Designated to be placed in "Fallen Idols" which is the first section of her book, The York Road
      1 leaf with envelope addressed to Miss Elizabeth L. Gilman
    - Tears. AMS, dated, 1912 April 11
      Gift of Mrs. Elizabeth L. Anderson in memory of Lawrence Gilman
  - REID, M.
    See: EDELWEISS, OTTO VON
  - REPPLIER, AGNES, 1855-1950, 3 (Box 24, Folder 910-912)
    - ALS to Eleanor, [Philadelphia], 1904 February 5
      Library associates, Gift of John W. Warrington, March, 1934
    - ANS to Edward (Augustus) Weeks, Jr., Philadelphia, 1938 June 7
    - 2 ALS, 1 APCS to James H. Penniman, Philadelphia, 1922-1929
      3 leaves with 3 addressed envelopes
    - ALS to Miss Alger, 4015 Locust Street, [Philadelphia], 1890 February 2
      Removed from: Her Points of view, Cambridge, 1892
    - ALS and ANS (on a calling card) to Mrs. Lionel Sutro, Philadelphia, Pa., 1908, undated
      Gift of Mrs. Louis K. Anspacher, 1957
    - Small Tragedies: typewritten copy, divided into four parts, "The stage," "Sin," "What claim had I?," and "Crime," with the author's MS corrections
      Gift of Richard E. Danielson, February 1941
    - Small Tragedies: galley-proofs with the author's MS corrections
    - ALS to Miss Abby (Langden) Alger, Philadelphia, Pa., 1889 February 24
    - ALS to Dr. Bixby, Philadelphia, Pa.
    - ALS to Mrs. Hodgdon, Philadelphia, Pa., November 22
  - REXROTH, KENNETH, 1905- (Box 24, Folder 913)
    - ALS to The Elizabethan Club, [New York], [1948 October 29]
      Gift of Herman W. Liebert, 1949
  - RICE, ALICE CALDWELL HEGAN, 1870-1942 (Box 25, Folder 914)
    - 7 ALS to Mr. Lichtig, Louisville, Ky., 1933-1936
  - RICE, CALE YOUNG, 1872-1943, 2 (Box 25, Folder 915-916)
    - ALS to William Griffith, Louisville, Ky., 1930 April 9
      With front of original envelope
      Removed from: Za copy of his Seed of the moon
    - ALS and TLS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Louisville, Ky., 1899, 1901
  - RICE, ELMER, 1892-1967 (Box 25, Folder 917)
    - 2 TLS to John Gassner, Stamford, Conn., 1947, 1949
  - RICE, GRANTLAND, 1880-1954 (Box 25, Folder 918)
    - TLS to Chairman, Cobb Dinner Committee, New York,, "Friday", undated
  - RICE, WALLACE, 1859-1939 (Box 25, Folder 919)
    - Typed copies of eight of his poems, with his autograph signature, 1896 April-December
      Presented to Eliot Flower
      Gift of Mrs. Paul Livingston, January 1934
  - RIDDLE, GEORGE, 1851-1910 (Box 25, Folder 920)
    - ANS to Miss (Abby Langden) Alger, [n. p.], [1881] December 28
  - RILEY, JAMES WHITCOMB, 1849-1916 (Box 25, Folder 921)
    - ALS to Elliott Flower, Indianapolis, 1904 February 8
      Gift of Dorothy Flower Livingston and Mrs. Elliott Flower, December. 1933
    - ANS to Robert Underwood Johnson, Indianapolis, 1895 June 5
      1 p,
      Gift of Mrs. William H. Coleman, July 1942
    - ALS to Mrs. Ella Farnum Pratt, Indianapolis, Ind., 1890 May 13
      Removed from: His Rhymes of childhood...1891 [i.e. 1890]
    - ALS to Anson Phelps Stokes, Indianapolis, 1902 June 19
    - ANS to Mrs. Yenowine, Indianapolis, 1890 February 21
    - When the Frost is on the Punkin; Autograph verse, [signed] (2 lines)
  - RINEHART, MARY ROBERTS, 1876-1958 (Box 25, Folder 922)
    - TLS to Mrs. Gerardus (?) P. Herrick, New York, 1948 May 8
    - TLS to Mrs. Robert Edwards, New York, 1948 April 3
  - RIVES, AMÉLIE, 1863-1945, 2 (Box 25, Folder 923-924)
    - ALS to Miss Dickinson, Cobham, Va., 1888 April 13
    - ALS to Mr. Stoddart, Castle Hill, 1892 September 2
      Removed from: Her The quick and the dead...[1888]
  - ROBERTS, CHARLES GEORGE DOUGLAS, SIR, 1860-1943, 2 (Box 25, Folder 925-926)
    - 2 ALS to his brother and/or sister- in-law, William Carman and Mary Fanton Roberts, Toronto, Ont., 1931, 1938
    - ALS to "My dear Russell," New York, 1903 June 26
      Russell is probably last name of member of L. C. Page firm, Roberts' publishers
      Removed from: Roberts' The Heart That Knows Boston, 1906 Alvord fund
    - [Inscription to Mary Annable [!] Roberts, dated], [1907 July]
      Removed from: his Poems (Boston
      1907)
    - Attar of Roses [poem], typescript
    - Be Quiet, Wind [poem], typescript (carbon)
      16 lines, Signed
    - A City Night [poem], manuscript
    - The Conspirators, autograph ms
      Poem of 22 lines
      Morse fund
    - Down the Ways of Dream [poem], manuscript, 1903 February
    - Forget not Thou [poem], typescript
      18 lines, Signed
    - Forget not Thou [poem], typescript, Toronto, Ont., 1940 May 26
      18 lines
    - The House [poem], manuscript
      26 lines, Signed (initials)
    - The Covert [poem], manuscript
      8 lines, Signed (initials)
      Written on p. 2 of his poem "The House"
    - The Iceberg [poem], typescript (carbon)
    - In Time of Earth's Misuse [poem], typescript, Toronto, Ont., 1940 February 9
      13 lines
    - The Nation [poem], manuscript, 1900 August 3
      32 lines, Signed
    - Presences [poem], typescript
      30 lines, Signed
      Inscribed to M[ary] F[anton] R[oberts]
    - To France, June 1940 [poem], typescript, dated, 1940 June 30
      14 lines
    - Unsaid [poem], typescript (carbon)
      12 lines, Signed
    - When in the Rowan Tree, autograph ms, 1903 March 15
      Signed, with initials
      Poem
      Purchased, Morse fund
      On conjugate leaf with his poem beginning "When the Cloud Comes Down the Mountain," autograph ms of same date, 1 leaf signed with initials
  - ROBERTS, THEODORE, 1861-1928 (Box 25, Folder 927)
    - TLS to Stephen B. French, Hollywood, 1926 June 15
  - ROBINSON, SELMA (Box 25, Folder 928)
    - 4 TLS and 2 ALS to James T(inkham) Babb, New York, 1932 January-October
  - ROE, EDWARD PAYSON, 1838-1888 (Box 25, Folder 929)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Cornwall-on-the-Hudson, 1888 May 10
    - ALS to Mr. Townsend, Cornwall-on- [the]-Hudson, 1883 July 17
      Alvord fund
      Removed from: his Success with small fruits, New York, 1882. Za.R622.880sc
  - ROETHKE, THEODORE, 1908-1963 (Box 25, Folder 930)
    - 3 ALS to Louis Lohr Martz, State College, Pa., New York, 1939, 1941, 1947
      [1939 letter enclosing carbon copy of Roethke bibliography]
      12 pages with 3 envelopes
      Gift of Louis L. Martz, May 1948
  - ROGÉ, CHARLOTTE FISKE (BATES), 1838-1916
    See: BATES, CHARLOTTE FISKE, 1838-1916
  - ROHLFS, ANNA KATHARINE (GREEN), 1846-1935
    See: GREEN, ANNA KATHARINE, 1846-1935
  - ROLLINS, ALICE WELLINGTON, 1847-1897 (Box 25, Folder 931)
    - 2 ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Brooklyn and New York, 1892
  - ROLLINS, CARL PURINGTON, 1880-1960 (Box 25, Folder 932)
    - [Bill Wilcox], typescript, 1942 September 9
      Signed and dated
      An epilogue to a printed poem distributed as a New Year's greeting from the Rollins family in 1925
  - ROOSEVELT, ELEANOR, 1884-1962 (Box 25, Folder 933)
    - TLS to Mr. Berolzheimer, Washington, D. C., 1941 November 18
      Thanking him for sending her photographs of her brother, Hall Gift of E. Leonard Sampter
  - ROWSON, MRS., 1762-1824 (Box 25, Folder 934)
    - Ms bill receipted and signed by her for the expenses of one term in the education of L[ydia] Champney, Newton, [Massachusetts], 1804 November 20
      Gift of Mrs. Alexander Cummins, November 1936
  - ROYALL, ANNE NEWPORT, 1769-1854 (Box 25, Folder 935)
    - ALS to O. L. Holley, Hartford, Conn., 1826 June 11
      Alvord fund, October 1942
  - RUFFIN, MARGARET ELLEN HENRY, d. 1941
    See: HENRY-RUFFIN, M. E. (MARGARET ELLEN), d. 1941
  - RUKEYSER, MURIEL, 1913-, 3 (Box 25, Folder 936-938)
    - 2 ALS to Mrs. James T. Babb, New York, 1955, 1956
    - 3 TNS to Pauline F. Stephens, New York, 1935 September-[October]
    - 3 TLS to the Yale University Library, New York, 1941-1942
      Concerns research for her book on Josiah Willard Gibbs
  - RULE, LUCIEN V., 1871-1948 (Box 25, Folder 939)
    - ALS to Edmund Clarence Stedman, Goshen, Kentucky, 1898 September 7
    - ALS to Arthur (Griffin) Stedman, Goshen, Kentucky, 1899 November 24
- "S"
  - SAINT-GAUDENS, AUGUSTUS, 1848-1907 (Box 25, Folder 940)